Guide to the Thomas B. Deen papers, 1957-1995
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Thomas B. Deen papers
1957-1995
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Deen, Thomas B.
C0106
26 linear feet (52 boxes)
The Thomas Blackburn Deen papers contain transportation-related materials collected between 1980 and 1994 while Mr. Deen was head of the National Research Council Transportation Research Board (TRB). Types of materials include conference and committee meeting materials, TRB research information, speeches and personal correspondence. The materials cover a wide variety of topics such as highway construction, safety, international transportation concerns, and funding for highways. Organizations represented by materials in the papers include the Federal Highway Administration, the Department of Transportation, and the Permanent International Association of Road Congresses.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the National Research Council Transportation Research Board.
Biographical Information
Born in 1928, Thomas Blackburn Deen, a graduate of the University of Kentucky, began his career as a highway traffic engineer. Early in his career, Deen pioneered the development and application of methods for analyzing urban transportation problems and designing urban transit systems. These computer-based analytical methods were used to evaluate and select the lines that today make up the Washington, D.C. area Metrorail system. Deen served as Director of Planning for the National Capital Transportation Agency from 1960 to 1964, and Executive Director of the National Research Council Transportation Research Board (TRB) from 1980 to 1994. At the TRB, Deen supervised policy studies on critical national transportation issues, such as the 55 mile per hour speed limit, school bus safety, air passenger service and safety since deregulation, intelligent vehicles, and high-speed rail. He was responsible for all of TRB's activities including its sponsorship of some 260 technical committees and panels, research retrieval systems, in house research, and state-sponsored cooperative research programs.
Scope and Content
The Thomas Blackburn Deen papers contain transportation-related materials collected between 1980 and 1994 while Mr. Deen was head of the National Research Council Transportation Research Board (TRB). Types of materials include conference and committee meeting materials, TRB research information, speeches and personal correspondence. The materials cover a wide variety of topics such as highway construction, safety, international transportation concerns, and funding for highways. Organizations represented by materials in the papers include the Federal Highway Administration, the Department of Transportation, and the Permanent International Association of Road Congresses. The collections is divided into six series.
Series 1 contains documents from and about meetings, conferences, conventions, workshops and other events that Deen was invited to or participated. Material includes agendas, schedules of events, contact lists, meeting minutes, articles, notes, speeches, correspondence, travel itineraries, travel receipts, publications, memos, programs, committee member lists, book excerpts, announcements, proposals, registration forms, travel vouchers, policy books, attendance lists, pamphlets, maps, resumes, lists of publications, organizational charts, flight schedules, business cards, contact information, essays, information tables, manuscripts, committee reports, overhead projector slides, photographs, financial information, calendars of events, newsletters, press releases, fact sheets, copyright information, slides, faxes and "Who's Who" listings. Subject matter includes infrastructure, transportation research, public works, civil engineering, hazardous material transportation, safety, financing infrastructure, pavement management and maintenance, technical policy, geometric design standards, energy usage, European infrastructure, transportation centers, traffic congestion, trucking, highway and transportation engineering, high speed trains, economics of transport, transportation law, mass transit, urban infrastructure, state highway and transportation officials, urban mobility, Australian transportation, The US Department of Transportation, motor vehicle manufacturers the future of transportation, transportation planning, Asian infrastructure, intelligent vehicles, aviation, and Indian highways. Series 1 also includes a subseries containing the lectures and speeches of Thomas Deen. At many of the events that Deen attended, he was invited to speak on a variety of topics. Material in this subseries includes transcripts of speeches, notes, programs, correspondence, travel information, maps, organizational charts, articles, pamphlets, schedules, agendas, newsletters, presentation slides, graphs and attendance lists. Subject matter includes Thomas Deen's life, the Transportation Research Board, the 55 mile per hour speed limit, the future of the automobile, economic growth and development, research, transportation, value engineering, citizens band radio in intercity busses, urban policy, trucking, hazardous materials, state and federal financial management, rapid transit, traffic congestion, transportation law, the role of state and region in public surface transportation, transportation centers, infrastructure, highway construction, engineering management, commencement addresses, transportation planning and scholarship.
Series 2 consists of research materials as well as documents from location tours. Material in this series includes research reports, correspondence, project status reports, memos, notes, travel information, articles, essays, organizational charts, budget information, publication lists, maps, research reports, newsletters, pamphlets, biographical sketches, agendas and project proposals. Subject matter includes road maintenance, automobile assembly, transportation policy, urban mobility, automobile safety, the Transportation Research Board, the US Army Corps of Engineers, intelligent vehicles, and testing.
Series 3 contains correspondence to and from Thomas Deen. Topics include travel, upcoming events, research, transportation, traffic laws, intelligent vehicles, transportation studies, Amnesty International, traffic management, transit research, highway administration and infrastructure.
Series 4 contains documents dealing with urban planning. Material includes booklets, receipts, newsletters, articles, correspondence, essays, notes, meeting agendas and schedules, memos, meeting minutes, presentation slides and Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society Planning Committee documents. Subject matter includes transportation planning on a federal and local level, traffic congestion, transportation engineering, and intelligent vehicles.
Series 5 contains published work by Thomas Deen. Subject matter includes transportation, rapid transit, transportation engineering, highway research, traveler response evaluation, transit planning, the Alan M. Voorhees and Associates firm, urban public transportation, public works, transportation planning, rail transit, bridge inspection, automotive safety, the 55 mile per hour speed limit, fiscal policies, growth, asphalt, labor, transportation statistics, Caracas, Venezuela, parking prices, planning, foreign highway research programs, urban transportation planning, and economic evaluation.
Series 6 contains miscellaneous files from the Thomas Deen collection. Material includes official reports, discussion outlines, meeting schedules and agendas, memos, correspondence, attendance lists, committee lists, work plans, travel information, notes, pamphlets, programs, resumes, newsletters, maps, articles, congressional resolutions, publications, fact sheets, business cards, contact information, charts and graphs, "Who's Who" articles and calendars. Subject matter includes public works, traffic management, vehicle safety, roads and bridges, carpooling, asphalt, the 55 mile per hour speed limit, traffic engineering, highway financing, federal highway administration, and railroads.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject.
Series 1: Meetings and Events, April 1962-October 1994 (Boxes 1-27)
Series 2: Research, September 1961-June 1993 (Boxes 27-31)
Series 3: Correspondence, August 1979-September 1995 (Boxes 31-34)
Series 4: Planning, April 1981-August 1994 (Boxes 34-36)
Series 5: Publications, February 1957-October 1995 (Boxes 36-48)
Series 6: Miscellaneous, January 1965-October 1995 (Boxes 48-52)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds many other transportation related collections and books.
Index Terms
Persons:
Deen, Thomas B.
Corporate Names:
American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials.; American Public Works Association.; American Road and Transportation Builders Association.; Institute of Transportation Engineers.; Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America.; International Road Federation.; National Asphalt Pavement Association.; National Research Council (U.S.). Transportation Research Board.; Permanent International Association of Road Congresses.; The Road Gang; United States. Dept. of Transportation.; United States. Federal Highway Administration.
Subjects:
Transportation, Automotive--United States.; Transportation Engineering--United States.; Transportation, Rail--United States.
Contents List
- Series 1: Meetings and Events, April 1962-October 1994
  Documents from and about meetings, conferences, conventions, workshops and other events that Deen was invited to or participated. Material includes agendas, schedules of events, contact lists, meeting minutes, articles, notes, speeches, correspondence, memos, programs, registration forms, pamphlets. Subject matter includes infrastructure, transportation research, public works, civil engineering, and safety. Also included is a subseries, consisting of transcripts of lectures and speeches given by Deen at various events and lectures.
  - Federal Highway Administration/Trandsportation Research Board Technology Transfer Activities, Febraury 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Asphalt Pavement Association-Annual Convention, August 1986-February 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ministry of Transportation- Canada Executive Committee Meeting and North American Conference on Managing Pavement, August-December 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Highway Users Federation 17th Annual Meeting, Westin Hotel, Washington D.C., November 1985-November 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Motor Vehicles Manufacturers Association Meeting, October-November 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Geometric Design Standards for Highway Improvements- Committee Meeting, September-October 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Public Works Association Congress and Equipment Show, New Orleans, Louisiana, April-September 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statewide Technical Policy Meeting, Orlando, Florida, September 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Asphalt Pavement Association, July-August 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Institute of Transportation Engineers District 617 Joint Meeting, Vancouver, British Columbia, March-July 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Roles of Private Enterprise and Market Process in the Financing and Provision of Roads, Baltimore, Maryland, February-July 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Truck Safety Meeting, Washington D.C., February-June 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Study on Improving Safety and Mobility of Older Persons, Washington, D.C., June 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Recent Advances in Hazardous Materials Transportation Research: An International Exchange, February-November 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Highway Research Opportunities for the Civil Engineer, Leesburg, Virginia, April 1984-July 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Public Works Association Research Foundation Meeting, Rosslyn, Virginia, February-May 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - World Conference on Transport Research, Vancouver, British Columbia, March 1985-March 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Countries, Washington D.C. Hilton, February-March 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1986 Program Evaluation Subcommittee (Highway Users Federation for Safety And Mobility), Baltimore, Maryland, September 1985-January 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Implications of Biotechnology- Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., December 1985-February 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Business Transportation Council 1982-84, June 1981-May 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transportion Research Board Energy Activities 1981-82, September 1981-January 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - University Transportation Center Peer Review, November-December 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Second North American Conference on Managing Pavements, Royal York Hotel Toronto, Canada, January-November 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International Pavement Maintenance-Management Technology Symposium Chicago, IL, October 1986-January 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Public Works Historical Society, Washington D.C., November 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American Public Work Association Board of Trustees Meeting, April-September 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brussels, January 1985-June 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gothenburg, August-September 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Linkoping, Stockholm, July 1987-October 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Western Conference of Research and Developments Managers, Boise, Idaho, June-August 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sixth International Conference on Structural Design of Asphalt Pavements- University of Michigan, June 1985-July 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association-National Truck Safety Symposium, Washington D.C., April-June 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Council of University Transportation Centers Executive Committee Meeting, Irvine, California, July 1986-June 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Highway Users Federation for Safety and Mobility Safety Conference, March-November 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Women's Transportation Seminar- National Conference, New York, November 1986-June 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Roads and Street Conference, Tucson, Arizona, January-May 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Massachusets Institute of Technology Center for Transportation Studies Advisory Committee Meeting, Cambridge, Massachusetts, November 1986-April 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - National Conference on Strategies to Alleviate Traffic Congestion, January-April 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Trucking Association Foundation National Symposium, December 1986-April 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Symposium on Technological Frontiers and Foreign Relations Dinner, March-May 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual Transportation Convention- South 1 of 2, January 1985-April 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Annual Transportation Convention- South 2 of 2, October 1984-August 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Transportation Executive Institute-University of Virginia, August-September 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Public Works Association Research Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting, Lebanon, New Hampshire, February-May 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Public Works Association Panel Moderator, Los Angeles, California, August-September 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Highway and Transportation Engineering Conference, February-March 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Alabama Highway Department, Montgomery, Alabama, February 1984-February 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - High Speed Trains Socio-Economic Aspects-French Ministry of Transportation Paris, France, December 1983-February 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - High Speed Trains Socio-Economic Aspects-French Ministry of Transportation Paris, France, February-November 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Parson Brinckerhoff Quade and Douglas meeting at Hunt Valley, MD, June-September 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Transportation Executive Institute-University of Virginia, October 1983-October 1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Economics of Transport in the 1980s Amalfi, Italy 1 of 2, December 1983-October 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Economics of Transport in the 1980s Amalfi, Italy 2 of 2, May 1984-March 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Visibility Symposium, March-July 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 23rd Workshop on Transportation Law, Rockport, Maine, March-July 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American Public Transit Association Columbus, Ohio, May 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Institute of Transportation Engineers, Washington, DC, April-May 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - National Issues in Science and Technology, December 1983-April 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Urban Mass Transportation Administration, December 1983-March 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Urban Institute Symposium, Washington, DC 1 or 2, June 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Urban Institute Symposium, Washington, DC 2 of 2, December 1983-April 1984 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Videotex Conference, Honolulu, Hawaii 1 of 2, October 1981-October 1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Videotex Conference, Honolulu, Hawaii 2 of 2, January 1982-March 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Technology Transfer, March 1980-January 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Transportation Research Board-American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials, December 1984-December 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Transportation Research Board-American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials, November-December 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Transportation Research Board Luncheon, March-December 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Meetings 1 of 2, May-June 1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Meetings 2 of 2, July-December 1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Executive Committee Meeting, April-June 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Milwaukee, Wisconsin, July-October 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Transportation Research Board Luncheon, September-December 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Transportation Research Board-American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Luncheon Atlanta, Georgia, August-November 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Luncheon, July-October 1993 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Luncheon Attendees, October 1993 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials Detroit, Michigan, August-October 1993 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials 1 of 2, January-April 1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials 2 of 2, September 1991-October 1992 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Procedures, August 1991-September 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Attendance, October 1992 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Script- Lunch, September-October 1992 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Joint Center for Urban Mobility Studies-Rice Center 1 of 2, January 1988-May 1989 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Joint Center for Urban Mobility Studies-Rice Center 2 of 2, May-September 1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Future Directions of Urban Public Transportation, September-October 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Urban Mass Transportation Administration Technical Assistance Seminar, November 1981-September 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Institute of Transportation Engineers- London August 1983, June 1982-August 1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Max Lay- Australia August 1982, May 1980-October 1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Australia Trip Arrangements, May-November 1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Women's Productivity Conference-National Academy of Sciences, October 1981-January 1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - American Road and Transportation Builders Association National Conference Local Transportation, Nashville, Tennessee, April-September 1981 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Institute of Transportation Engineers-51st Annual Meeting, Boston, Massachusetts, June-September 1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 20th Annual Workshop on Transportation Law, Burlington, VT, July 1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - International Road Federation World Meeting, Stockholm 1981 1 of 2, March-November 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - International Road Federation World Meeting, Stockholm 1981 2 of 2, June 1980-June 1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Truck Safety Meeting, April-May 1981 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - International Symposium on Surface Transportation System Performance, May 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - International Symposium on Surface Transportation System Performance, August 1980-July 1981 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Transport Tomorrow Conference, March 1981-May 1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Taiwan Conference 1 of 2, October-December 1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Taiwan Conference 2 of 2, September-December 1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Federal Highway Administration-Transportation Research Board, August 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - American Trucking Association, August-September 1988 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Aviation Owners and Pilots Association-Lunch, April-October 1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - American Public Works Association Foronts, April-October 1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Highway Users Federation, August-September 1988 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - American Road and Transportation Builders Association, July-September 1988 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association/Department of Transportation, May-August 1988 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 2020 Futures Conference 1988, June 1987-June 1989 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Transportation Research Board Future Conference, December 1986-July 1988 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Conference on State Role in Public Transportation, May-June 1988 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - American Public Works Association-Cleveland, March-May 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Institute of Transportation Engineers, Reston, Virginia, March-April 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Western Highway Institute, February-May 1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Highway Research Coordinating Council, Gaithersburg, Maryland, February-April 1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Urban Land Institutue/Urban Mass Transportation Administration- Suburban Mobility, Chicago, December 1987-April 1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Transportation 2020, January 1986-April 1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development, Paris, France, December 1987-March 1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 3rd International Road Federation Middle East Meeting- Saudi Arabia, February 1987-July 1988 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Highway Users Federation Forum, San Antonio, Texas, October 1987-February 1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Transportation Systems Center Meeting, Boston, Massachusetts, May 1987-January 1988 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America- Tactical Planning Workshop 1 of 2, July 1992 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America- Tactical Planning Workshop 2 of 2, June-August 1992 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America Annual Meeting, January-August 1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America- Newport Beach, California, February-May 1992 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Strategic Planning Workshop, June 1991-October 1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minutes and Meetings 1991-92, April 1992-January 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway Society of America, March 1980-May 1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes and Meetings 1991-92, July 1991-April 1992 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Minutes and Meetings 1991-92, March-July 1991 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania Transportation Conference, September-November 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - National Seminar on Asphalt Pavement and Recycling, Dallas, Texas, October 1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National Committee on Uniform Traffic Laws and Ordnances, August 1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)